Hello, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
about oxidation and reduction
of carbohydrates, specifically
simple sugars or monosaccharides.
So with these, what we're going to
be using is we're going to be looking
at Fischer projections, which are
when you take, let's say, if you
take a Hayworth projection and you
are to open it up, we're going to go
through all the different reactions
in a very simple to follow manner.
We're going to go through
all the different types of
strong and weak oxidation.
as well as reduction and
enzyme oxidation as well.
So let's take a look
at what I have for you.
Okay, the first thing is that all
monosaccharides can be oxidized.
So when that Haworth or that
cyclic shape opens up and unfolds,
it is able to be oxidized.
Now you might be thinking back to
organic and you might be thinking that,
well, can't only aldehydes oxidize?
Well, one thing that can happen with,
with these type of chemicals with
aldehydes and ketones is that they can
isomerize between the two, meaning they
can rearrange each rearrange themselves.
So it's like taking a bunch of Legos and
rebuilding a completely different shape.
So the C double bond O can
move from carbon number one to
carbon number two as a result.
So when it moves from one to the other.
It makes this oxidation possible
when it is an aldose, right?
So aldoses can be oxidized.
So we need this shape on the left.
But this can happen naturally
in your body through oxidation,
through the proper, through
proper, uh, channels using enzymes.
So like using an isomerase enzyme.
They can be rearranged through metabolism.
Let's take a look at the different
types of reactions that we'll have.
Okay.
In front of us, we have D galactose, which
is a simple sugar or a monosaccharide.
Now the whole thing that we're going
to be doing here is we're going to be
first looking at how can this structure
change and how can we identify it?
Now the first thing is, it's
all about naming, right?
Naming an IUPAC is very important.
So if we see that OSE ending
in the name, that's telling you
that you have a simple sugar.
We can see that ending up here
in the aldose before as well.
Same thing we learned
about classifying them too.
So if I were to put this through
a reduction reaction, usually it's
represented by an H because we're
going to be adding hydrogen to it.
So usually it's either represented
with an H in brackets or maybe
with H2 being added as well.
One or the other.
Because the idea behind these is the only
thing changing is the functional groups.
Now, what sets an aldose apart is that
it has an aldehyde at the very top of it.
This is going to be changing.
So how can that happen?
Well, if you think of a double
bond as a cabinet, now, if I
open up the doors of the cabinet,
We're going to be adding hydrogen.
to that part of the double bond.
So what I like to do is when we are to
do these to help you remember oxidation
reduction is I always try to color
code and change our different labels.
So if I look at my double bond here,
imagine the blue line as a, as your
cabinet, and we're going to open it.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, I'm going to open it
where one door opens on the H,
the other door opened on the C.
And what are you going to be adding
to both sides is a hydrogen, right?
And now what did you make?
Now we have a primary alcohol as a result.
So that one prime alcohol
is a product of reduction.
Now, specifically, this is known
as a sugar alcohol, okay, so it
went from a simple sugar to a
sugar alcohol, which has a name.
This is known as an alditol,
which has the ending ital Now,
how can I go through and name it?
Well, before it was galactose.
So we're going to keep the
beginning part, and it's going to
be Galactitol as the ending, right?
We have the I T O L
ending as our change here.
So let's color code that so it
matches from above, and we'll do
the same thing with our os as well.
All right, so that's one.
Now, what about if I want to
go through the opposite way?
What if I want to go through oxidation?
What exactly can I do?
Well, with this, we can go through
weak oxidation and we can form aldonic
acid, which in this case is if you
go oxidation, we're adding oxygens.
This is going to make
a sugar acid instead.
So sugar acid, if you go one way,
sugar alcohol, if you go the other.
Now, when we see this, this
oxidation process, this is known
as a weak oxidation, which is
going to differ from strong.
Weak oxidation, typically the
way that you see that in a lab
setting is if you're adding like
Benedict's reagent, Tollens reagent.
It's all about just changing a
aldehyde to a carboxylic acid.
So let's try that.
So if I have the following, what, the
only thing that's going to be changing
is the functional group, which is on
top, and we're going to be adding an OH
to it to help make that carboxylic acid.
all the way at the top.
So see the C double bond O
and the OH attached to it.
So how would I change the name?
Well, before it was galactose.
So it's going to, we're going to
keep the galact part, and then
we will change the ending cold to
galactonic acid as the name, right?
So just like, so, so we have
our sugar acid and on the far
left, we have the sugar alcohol.
And in the middle, we just
have a regular simple sugar.
And that's the idea of
oxidation reduction.
Is this all that's possible in your body?
Well, your body is a complex place.
There's all kinds of other
reactions that are possible too.
Let's take a look at the last two
and see what else is possible.
Okay, the other oxidation reaction you
can have is between weak and strong.
And generally in organic and biochemistry,
depending on what reagents are adding,
you can specify the difference in
how you are conducting an experiment.
So if you have a strong oxidation, what
this is going to do, it's going to oxidize
two different points on your molecule.
The first place it's going to oxidize
is going to be the same idea as before.
So usually we have oxidation and
typically we'll just call it strong.
So the first one is going to match what
we did on our last problem, where we
add a carboxylic acid on the very top.
Now, where else can it be oxidized?
Well, think about where,
where's the most vulnerable?
Where is there a maybe a primary alcohol
that's ready to react and that's going to
be right down here at the bottom, right?
There is a primary alcohol down here.
So what can happen just to
kind of and let's color code
these just to show them Right.
So we have the one on top now the one on
the bottom can also go through oxidation
as well We can make a C double bond O, OH,
because there's hydrogens ready to react.
So you have two carboxylic acids,
or a dicarboxylic acid, as a result.
Okay, now when it comes to the
naming, it's still going to follow
very similar ideas as before.
This is still a sugar acid.
But this is going to have the aric ending
all the way that we see up top, okay?
So if we kind of copy that down for
ourselves, we're going to take the
galactose part to the galact And it's
going to be galactaric Acid as a name
and being that this is degalactaric
acid you're going to keep that letter
for the sugar Acids and I should
have done the last one as well.
They're both D-galactaric,
Galactaric and D-galactonic acid.
Okay, so the ending changes to
let you know, how oxidized is it?
Let's take a look at the last one in
terms of how your body works with enzymes.
Last type of oxidation there can be in
terms of the metabolic processes for
the basic of reactions is when an aldose
reacts specifically with an enzyme.
Remember, enzymes are specific.
They choose exactly what they want to
react with because these molecules fit
and bind with them a very specific way.
So one way that an enzyme can react with
an aldose is that it can specifically
select primary alcohols to oxidize.
So if I have the same idea
here where I have a reaction.
And I'm saying that, oh, this is
an enzyme reaction, then how can I
respect that particular reaction?
Where can it react?
So where is there a primary alcohol?
So if we look closely, you gotta try
to remember how do you pick primaries.
Well, the whole idea is that you
look at the alcohol, you look at
the carbon next to it, and you see
how many carbons is that bound to.
If you look closely at the bottom
here, right, so kind of put a
little star here, that carbon is
connected to only one other carbon.
Making it primary.
So it's a candidate for
enzyme, an enzyme reaction.
So what that means is, the bottom
alcohol, or alcohol here is going
to rearrange itself to become
a C double bond O with an OH.
So we have another sugar acid that is
going to form, but only on the bottom.
The top is still an aldehyde.
So just to kinda Highlight that, right?
It's still an aldehyde.
There's no change to the top.
It only picks primary
alcohol is where that reacts.
So when that happens, this is
going to have a very specific name.
So being that that one on the left
was D galactose, the one on the right
is going to be D galacturonic acid.
It sounds like something out of Star Wars.
So it's going to be D galacturonic acid
is how we would name that structure.
And that would be your final oxidation
reduction on how you can understand
and see all these different reactions.
I hope that this video helped and
if it did, please hit that like and
subscribe button and I hope to see
you around for future introductory
organic and biochemistry videos.
I hope you all have a wonderful
day and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.